ONE HUNDRED YEARS OF SOLITUDE
Hello?
Does this home belong to
José Arcadio Buendía?
Yes.
Who is it, Amaranta?
Morning.
Rebeca arrived on a Sunday.
She had made the difficult trip
from Manaure with some hide dealers
who had taken on the task
of delivering her
along with the bones of her parents.
What's it say?
That she's
some distant cousin of ours,
daughter of the indelible Nicanor Ulloa
and his noble wife, Rebeca Montiel.
Daughter of whom?
But they
could not explain precisely
who had asked them for the favor.
What is your name?
Are you hungry?
Aureliano,
Arcadio will sleep in your room.
-Sure.
-Visitación, prepare a bath.
Can I move
into Aureliano's room?
No, Arcadio is old enough
to room with your brother.
Bring me a dress you don't wear anymore.
But…
We have enough men in this house.
Another girl will do us both good.
You can trust a sister with anything.
Understand?
Now, help me.
The dress, Amaranta!
Bones?
Uh-huh.
Many bones.
I won't ask you again.
Let's go.
I don't know when this house
became some kind of orphanage.
As if Arcadio wasn't enough already.
Aureliano had the patience
to read to her
the names of all the saints,
but she did not react to any of them.
Lucía.
Dorotea.
Inés.
What if she's a deaf-mute?
Well, regardless,
we'll call her Rebeca, like her mother.
Period.
Now, leave her be.
Hey!
Want me to tell mom what you're up to?
Go to sleep.
I'm not tired yet, though.
Liar.
You're afraid to sleep near the freak.
That's not true.
Besides, you're just the same as she is.
A kid without any parents.
Amaranta…
May I sleep in your room tonight?
You'll sleep in yours
just fine.
So?
Come on. Come with me.
Do you know what that is?
Armadillo?
It starts with the letter "A."
Like "Arcadio."
"A."
Do you know this letter right here?
It… it's "B"?
Very good.
Bedtime, Arcadio.
We'll continue tomorrow.
Good night.
Do you think we need someone else
caged up in this laboratory?
If we can feed seven,
we can feed eight.
She hasn't eaten anything
since she got here. Not one bite.
She'll come running
to you the minute her stomach rumbles.
It's not Rebeca that I'm worried about.
It's Aureliano.
He hasn't come out of that laboratory
since the day his brother left.
As if he's afraid of the world.
Aureliano, come here!
Have a coffee with your old man.
Morning.
You know, believe it or not,
when I was around your age,
I had already met your mother.
It seemed as though the whole town
knew we would end up together.
But we were completely oblivious.
Or at least, I was.
Why do you lock yourself
in that room all day, son?
Are you selling
those little fish you make?
Why don't you go for a walk, Aureliano?
There are things in life
that you'll never find inside that room.
I can't believe you're saying that.
Did your mother ask you
to tell you to tell me that?
No.
The difference is that unlike you, son,
I lived a full life
before locking myself in here.
And if it hadn't been for that,
we'd have no Macondo,
no you,
nor anything that makes up your world.
Go on, go for a walk.
Those little fish of yours
aren't going anywhere.
-Hello.
-Evening.
Can I please have a liter of acid?
And some gold sheets.
Appreciate it, sir.
Amaranta, Rebeca!
Time to eat!
"U… A…"
Let's pause this for now, Arcadio.
Get the spoons.
Cataure! Where's Rebeca?
-Do you need help, Dad?
-No, it's almost ready.
What's wrong with you?
Look at your hair and look at Amaranta's.
It's been a day, Rebeca.
You must eat.
Rebeca, everyone knows that in this house,
we serve the best yam soup.
Have a little.
You're not leaving
until you finish.
I dare you, muchachita.
If you want to starve yourself, go ahead.
But we don't waste food in this house.
Cataure! Take the bag.
Rebeca.
Stop her!
Stay still!
Come on now.
Stop it.
Let's give it a rest for a second, senora.
It doesn't work that way.
My house, my rules!
Go shove that drink
up your ass.
What'd she say?
-You can shove that bowl up your--
-Out!
Just a little taste, Rebeca.
And then I'll let you be.
I promise, all right?
All I want is for you to be okay.
Thank you,
Mama.
My girl.
Do you all wanna hear
the story of the old capon?
Yes.
I didn't ask you to say "yes."
I asked you if you all wanna hear
the story of the old capon.
Then don't.
I didn't ask you to say, "then don't."
I asked you if you wanted to hear
the story of the old capon.
Give it a break, Rebeca.
You'll make them go insane.
More, please?
Some more?
Thank you, Mama.
You're not hungry, sister?
It's the best yam soup in all of Macondo.
Oh, really? Did you add dirt or what?
Amaranta!
Eat your soup.
I dare you.
Cataure.
Do you hear that?
Mm. An animal got in, or…
…something.
Cataure, let's go.
-Mm.
-Let's go.
Rebeca?
Visitación and Cataure
recognized in those eyes the symptoms
of a terrible illness.
Cataure fled
and never returned.
It was the insomnia plague.
It has been a long time
since you left your home.
Those are just tales.
But they're not tales, sir.
Visitación.
No!
-You better not put your finger in there.
-Don't you think you're exaggerating?
No, ma'am. I am not.
Listen to me now.
As soon as the plague enters the house,
no one ever sleeps again.
Oh please, Visitación.
That's just superstition.
And if it's real and we never sleep again,
even better.
We'll get more out of this life.
Take them to the plaza
once we finish these.
A little fresh air will be nice.
Get some candy animals!
Candy animals!
Come get some candy animals.
Here, have some candy animals.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Thanks, Rebeca.
Here, chicken,
chicken, chicken, chicken, chicken!
He got out!
The Buendías
did not become alarmed
until their third day with no sleep.
Imagine the things we could do
with all this time.
There we go.
Let's fill this plaza with almond trees.
Great idea, my friend.
Thanks for coming.
-Ha! I win!
-What?!
-No, no, no, no, no!
-Twelve! Fourteen to twelve.
No, no, no, no, no. No, no.
The most fearsome
part of the illness
was not the impossibility of sleep,
for the body did not feel
any fatigue at all.
Dad! Pass me the, uh…
The what?
Rather, it was
its inexorable evolution
towards a more critical state.
Oblivion.
ALMOND TREE
Aureliano conceived the strategy
that would protect them
against the inevitable loss of memory.
WALL
ANVIL
They went on living
in a reality that was slipping away…
COAL
…momentarily captured by words…
BIRD: FLYING CREATURE
STOVE: ALL FOOD MUST BE HEATED
…until they too began to vanish,
as did the meaning of letters.
HAMMER MILL: PUT CORN IN, GRIND
Then the names.
PIG SLAUGHTERING KNIFE
Then the notion of all things.
EGGS: LAID BY CHICKENS
USE FIRE TO LIGHT THESE CANDLES
DON'T PEE IN THE STREETS
PEOPLE GET ANGRY
STREETLIGHT
MILK THE COW EVERY MORNING
BOIL MILK BEFORE MAKING COFFEE WITH MILK
My friend, things are getting complicated.
Who are you?
What do you mean, who am I, brother?
Get out!
Rapist! Rapist! Rapist!
Wait, wait! He's your husband!
Let go of me!
Thief! Hey!
Get down from there!
Catarino!
He who has no teeth
shall drink, my friend!
GOD EXISTS
Úrsula! Go get the children!
Hey, Buendía!
You know, maybe that fighting cock
can finally do your wife a favor.
Go home and find a weapon
'cause I'm gonna kill you.
Prudencio?
And then, finally,
the insomnia plague would strip away
their very sense of self,
sinking them into a state
of idiocy that had no past.
José Arcadio! José Arcadio!
What is it? What's happening?
Who are you?
He's a gypsy now.
Run back home,
tell your father what happened.
What's it feel like?
Like the whole world
is shaking.
Devoid of the supernatural
faculties he once possessed,
Melquiades returned to Macondo.
It was true he had experienced death,
but he had come back,
being unable to bear the solitude.
DOOR
SEAT
Can I help you, sir?
What is this place?
Your alchemical laboratory.
My laboratory?
Sh.
Melquiades!
They told me you were dead.
Sit down.
But why?
COLUMN
BEING IN THE SUN FOR LONG
MAKES ME ANGRY
CHAIR
INKWELL
So, this thing's able to capture time?
But how, Melquiades?
I mean that's impossible.
You must be patient, José Arcadio.
You'll see it for yourself.
Úrsula!
-We're ready!
-I'm coming!
Aureliano! Come!
Aureliano had shot up so fast,
he started wearing his father's clothes.
From the confines of the workshop
he shared with Melquiades,
one could scarcely hear him breathe.
Rebeca was the fairest daughter.
Her complexion was immaculate.
She had large and peaceful eyes
and magical hands that seemed to
embroider designs with invisible threads.
Rebeca, come here!
Amaranta was somewhat plain,
but she had the natural distinction
and refinement of Petronila,
her late grandmother.
Amaranta, now!
And although he was already
showing the physical drive of his father…
Arcadio!
…Arcadio looked like a child,
and some said he had a woman's buttocks.
Mm-hmm. Very nice.
Wait… Like that. There.
Hmm. What are these?
Didn't Visitación make you
some bigger pants?
A few months ago, yeah.
Go get changed.
-Go. José Arcadio.
-Huh?
What's going on?
What?
You look like a frightened general.
What about you?
Me, no.
If that machine does what you say it does,
I will not be mocked by my grandchildren.
Hmm.
Stay still.
Well, that's it. We got it.
Arcadio.
Go to the Arab's shop. Get some mercury.
You can be my assistant.
Of course.
Careful. Slowly.
Sh, sh, sh, sh, sh. Ah. Just a bit more.
-There.
-There?
-Yes.
-Perfect.
Come on.
Now, very carefully,
nice and slow…
Voilà.
Your family.
Now we let it dry.
If this machine contains time and space,
and everything in between,
then it's able to capture God.
I knew you would love this thing,
but get that idea out of your head.
Teach me how it works.
-Teach me how it works!
-All right.
Dry the plate.
So, what's first?
-We polish.
-That's our plate.
-Yes.
White, red and black,
in that order.
Take your time.
Good. That's enough white.
And now black.
In the family daguerreotype,
the only one to ever exist,
Aureliano had the same clairvoyant look
that he would have years later
as he faced the firing squad.
But he still had not sensed
the premonition of his own death.
-Well, well, well.
-It's him.
Hey, Aureliano! Come here!
Hey, my friend.
It's a miracle seeing you
out of the house.
No, the only miracle is seeing you sober
at this time of day, Gerineldo.
Hey, give him a break. At least he's here.
How are you? It's nice to see you.
Good, Magnífico. And you?
I'm fine, I'm fine.
You ran out of oil.
Some of us actually work,
know what I mean?
And what's all that money
even good for, huh?
If you can't have rum with your amigos?
Pay up, my friend.
Catarino! Look who's here!
Aurelito! Mijo.
Aren't you a sight for sore eyes, son?
-Hey, Catarino.
-Make yourself at home.
-How's the family?
-They're doing well. How about you?
I'm doing well.
-Hey, give your dad my best, yeah?
-Of course.
Give us three rums, will you?
Gentlemen! For just a few days in Macondo!
The one and only, the best, Eréndira!
It's only 20 centavos for her time!
The Innocent Eréndira.
That's the mulatta
everyone's been talking about.
They say she's beautiful,
a remarkable woman. Go for it.
-No, I'm good. Thank you.
-Hey, come on, now.
Look, this is an experience
worthy of a Buendía.
Hey.
You're still a virgin.
You're still a virgin!
We're fixing that today.
-You ready?
-Come on.
-All right, let's go.
-Wait, wait.
-No, no, no.
-No, no, no, no, no.
-You relax, my friend.
-Follow me.
-We've got business to take care of…
-I just came for acid.
Get the acid later!
-Hey. Hey, hey, hey.
-Just go. Fine. Enough.
Be quick about it.
My friends encouraged this.
I was told to toss twenty centavos
in the tray and to be quick about it.
Tossing another twenty on your way out
will buy you a little more time.
Wait.
-Have I done something wrong?
-No, no.
You haven't.
Do you ever rest?
Once my grandma's repaid, I can rest.
The woman standing outside?
Around two years ago,
I lit a candle and fell asleep.
When I woke up, I was surrounded by fire.
And the house turned to ashes.
How much do you owe her?
Uh, at the moment,
seventy men per night
for… ten years.
You're beautiful.
Thank you.
Then I will throw in 20 pesos.
But that's a lot.
One hundred men.
What's the matter?
Nothing.
-Are you all right?
-Yes.
Hey, why don't you go to the lab
if you want to read?
I've had a long day.
Aureliano?
I was just a kid, but…
but Visitación always talks about
how you foresaw the arrival
of Rebeca months ahead.
Is that true?
It is.
Does that mean you saw mine?
You know,
all of us are completely and desperately
alone in this world.
And knowing who your parents are
won't make a difference.
Rebeca.
-You have no shame, do you?
-Why would I?
You're my sister.
We should always confide
in one another as sisters.
Otherwise, who's gonna keep your secrets
when you sneak out with your boyfriends?
With whom? You're insane.
Well, look.
See, as soon as you go outside in this,
they'll all be circling you like flies.
-Hmm!
-No… no. Rebeca. Stop!
Give me the towel!
-Rebeca, give me the towel!
-No!
Rebeca! Give me the towel!
What's going on in here?
Why are you naked?
Úrsula suddenly realized
that her daughters
were old enough to marry.
And as if she had contracted
her husband's hallucinating fever,
she undertook the expansion of the house.
Listen up, boys!
I need a dining room big enough
that it can hold a table for 12.
All right? Well, go ahead. Go on. Here.
And for this room, right here,
it will be a large hall decorated
with the finest Viennese furniture,
and we will host the most
distinguished parties in the swamp.
Yes? You understand?
Follow me.
Damn you, I just swept.
Now I have to start over.
This way.
The windows in all nine bedrooms
should face the patio.
Separate bathrooms
for the men and for the women,
and a kitchen large enough for two stoves.
-Understood?
-Understood.
Move!
Everyone, stay still.
Stop!
Hello.
-Are you Mrs. Úrsula Buendía?
-Yes.
Pietro Crespi.
Nice to meet you.
I brought your order
from the capital.
I brought you
some lemonade, Mr. Crespi.
Thank you very much,
ma'am.
How long
is that going to take?
Hmm.
Signora, I'm not sure.
You see, it's a complex instrument.
It will take a while.
Signorine, a… apologies.
Hello.
Pietro Crespi. Nice to meet you.
Rebeca.
Amaranta Buendía. Pleasure.
Welcome.
Thank you.
Well, how long
is it going to take Mr. Crespi?
Signora,
about a week, give or take.
Yes. But with your permission,
I could teach your daughters how to dance.
I don't know if you know this, but lessons
are included with the instrument.
Hmm.
Right. I appreciate you offering.
-But that isn't necessary.
-Of course.
Mother, that would be perfect.
Aren't we throwing a party
so we can celebrate the new house?
And for our presentation into society.
Fine.
But Arcadio will be
with the two of you at all times.
And no touching either.
Of course, ma'am.
All right, off you go.
Let him work.
While José Arcadio
kept chasing after
God's ubiquitous, invisible traces…
Pietro continued to work with a dedication
much like that of Aureliano
in his silverwork.
What's the matter, José Arcadio?
I can sense you're upset over something.
I don't understand.
What don't you understand?
How is it that I've captured
every corner of Macondo,
and God didn't present
himself in any of them?
Oh, my dear friend.
Is that really how you imagined God?
Let's begin by correcting our posture.
Relax your shoulders.
-Don't be so obvious.
-Sh!
Stretch out your arms
and remember…
One, two, three.
One, two, three. One, two, three.
Very good.
One, two, three.
Now grab a partner.
One, two, three. One, two, three.
One, two, three. One, two, three. One…
What's that?
He's inside the pianola.
Who?
God.
José Arcadio,
you're not making any sense at all.
Maybe you should worry
about your daughters.
-And why should I?
-What do you mean why?
-Isn't it obvious?
-What is it, huh?
Their virtue.
Stop being preoccupied about their virtue.
That man's a fairy.
It has been a pleasure, Rebeca.
Signorina Amaranta.
Signora Úrsula.
Thanks for everything.
It has been wonderful.
I promise I'll return.
Are you coming to bed?
What have you done?
I needed to know how it works. You see--
In two days,
every single one of our friends is coming.
And they'll be coming with their sons,
potential suitors for both your daughters.
So you better figure out
how to put that thing back together!
-Beautiful night for a party, yes?
-Yes.
-See you inside.
-Thank you.
-How are you?
-Good evening.
Thank you so much.
-Ah! My dear friend.
-Thank you.
Thank you.
Come in, please. Come in. Thank you.
-Welcome, welcome.
-Úrsula!
-How are you? Good evening.
-Nice to see you.
Thank you. After you.
Visitación, please start
serving the biscuits, will you?
It was nearly 30 years ago
that we packed our things
and left that town.
And we decided to create a new home.
We created this with our own bare hands,
in the middle of nowhere.
Who knows
where José Arcadio and I would be
had you all not had the faith
to join us in this mad adventure.
All right then, dear friend.
Did you invite us here to cry or what?
I mean, am I right?
Not at all, Magnífico.
But I wasn't
about to pass up the opportunity
to tell you that I've never forgotten
that what we built belongs to everyone.
And that it would be an honor
for our families to come together
through our daughters.
Well, that is if your boys
are ready for a bit of competition.
Well, then let the party begin!
-Hear! Hear!
-Let's hear it!
Huh.
Rebeca, may I have this dance?
-You look beautiful tonight.
-Oh, thank you.
So, should we show them how it's done?
Uh, pardon me, sir. May I cut in?
You are the fairest woman
in all of Macondo, Rebeca Buendía.
Pietro?
Rebeca, are you all right?
Son, wait!
The handfuls of earth
made her feel closer to the only man
worthy of such a display of degradation.
Are you still angry at me?
No, I am not angry at you, José Arcadio.
I'm scared.
-Is this the Buendía residence?
-Yes, sir.
It's an urgent message.
You're hereby notified.
Good evening.
Excuse me.
Someone dropped this off.
Sent by the government.
Sent by the government?
He said
we're hereby notified.
Notified?
It says that we all must
paint our houses blue.
Come on. Says who, exactly?
The Judicial Officer of Macondo,
appointed by the Government of Colombia.
Can they do that? Judicial Officer?
What officer?
Who in the hell is Apolinar Moscote?
BASED ON THE NOVEL
BY GABRIEL GARCÍA MÁRQUEZ